Douglas Waugh - Developer

Contact Details

Mobile phone number: 07863546306

Email address: douglas.waugh.e3@gmail.com

Postal address: 8 Brighton Avenue, London, E17 7NE

Introduction

Development Methodology

I write easy to understand, easy to change code that works. I focus on delivering the highest value to the business in the shortest possible time.

In order to do this I utilise several tools and techniques. These include maintaining a dialog with the customers and quality assurers throughout the development process, building and releasing vertical slices incrementally, developing testing strategies, writing my code test-first, refactoring both test and production code, and using an automated continuous integration and delivery pipeline.

Primarily I've coded on the Windows stack in C# and SQL but I am also experienced in building single page applications in Javascript using AngularJS. I've written some Python and I've even started to learn a little Ruby.

I'm comfortable using the CQRS+ES architectural pattern, and have some experience working with services communicating using those events.

Personal Development

I am committed to my own personal development and I find there are so many interesting subjects within the industry. I've usually got a technical book on the go (currently 'Continuous Delivery') and attend events in London's thriving development community.

I've been a regular attendee of XProLo meetup, it's predecessor Extreme Tuesday Club and the associated conference XPDay as well as the London Software Craftsmanship meetups, particularly those of a practical nature. Recently I've started attending PaaS and Serverless meetups, excited by the possibilities such platforms can bring to the development build and release process, and the London Continuous Delivery meetup. I'm also interested in machine learning and data science.

I continue to use pet projects and code katas to learn new technologies and improve my technical skills.

Work Experience

energyhelpline.com, Southwark, London

energyhelpline.com are a medium scale (2 million comparisons per month, 1 million switches per year) price comparison site for domestic energy products. They don't have much of a brand presence themselves but are, along with uSwitch and MoneySuperMarket, one of the big three energy comparison companies. Compare The Market use our RESTful energy switching API and energyhelpline has over 100 partners who use their comparison and switching products including major newspapers. Some 'tier 2' energy suppliers even use their services for their own websites and call centres.

Apr 2017 - Present : Tech Lead

Apr 2014 - Apr 2017 : Senior Developer

Jan 2012 - Apr 2014 : Analyst Developer

After WTG I looked specifically for a company offering me freedom over my personal development process, particularly with respect to writing tests first and working in an agile manner. energyhelpline.com fitted the bill.

I have worked on and delivered some of energyhelpline's most important and successful projects over the last few years. Amongst other things a Richardson Maturity Model Level 3 RESTful energy comparison and switching API, relied on by Compare The Market, and a rebuild of our own publicly facing site to use that API using AngularJS, www.energyhelpline.com which I ended up leading.

I developed more of an understanding for application architecture gaining experience working with the CQRS+ES architectural patterns spanning multiple services that the energyhelpline code base is built with. With this knowledge, and that of object oriented design, test driven development and the REST architectural style, I acted as a de-facto lead developer whilst the team was without a Tech Lead, providing technical solutions for the business and supporting other developers with their design and architectural decisions. In April 2017 I was rewarded with an official promotion to Tech Lead.

I have improved the speed and accuracy of our development by cultivating a truly test driven culture within the team, introducing automated deployments, continuously improving the deployment pipeline, and developing testing strategies. Whilst I work at energyhelpline.com, I will continue to try and improve it further.

One of my ex-colleagues told me I'd been responsible for the change in culture at energyhelpling.com. It was never my intention to change the culture of the team, I just did the things that I thought we should be doing, tried to encourage others to do the same and, when I had the opportunity, hired people who I believed had similar values to myself.

I did try and improve our recruitment. I brought a new recruiter on board who understood our

needs, I changed the messaging in our job specifications, got the team to silicon milkroundabout, and started and contributed to the tech blog http://tech.energyhelpline.com to improve our visibility to the development community.

I was lucky enough to work with some good developers at energyhelpline.com, and there is no doubt that I'm a better programmer for it.

WTG Technologies Ltd, Hammersmith, London

WTG Technologies Ltd is a design and build agency, spun out of their parent company Cable & Wireless, with a strong focus on government clients requiring a high level security, such as the MoJ and police forces. They provide security cleared staff and have a direct link in to some secure government networks.

Nov 2007 - Jan 2012 : Junior C# Developer to Tech Lead

I worked on several projects, ending up as technical lead on a web application to aid the police with collaboration called POLKA. I also worked on DORS, a web application to enable people who had committed driving offenses to register for training schemes, and part of a multi-million pound solution to deliver a content managed help and information site for the 2011 UK Census.

I started my journey towards becoming a better, more fully engaged developer at WTG and implementing and evangelising about XP practices and techniques to improve the quality of our code and projects. The unit tests I wrote were the first units tests I'd written and the first written on the projects I worked on. I set up a continuous integration server, automated deployments, and tried, with limited success, to get my team mates pairing.

I managed to add an element of agility to the projects I worked on, particularly POLKA, by asking for work items to be prioritised enabling more important functionality to be delivered sooner, and having a member of the clients team work with us at our office one day a week, increasing the speed with which we could deliver working features by reducing the lag between communication and the accuracy of our work by improving the quality of the communication between the developers and the client.

E3Media Ltd, Bristol

A design and build agency who, at the time I worked for them, built mainly brochure-ware websites and websites to support ad campaigns.

Aug 2006 - Nov 2007: Freelance Tester to Junior C# Developer

During two week's unpaid work experience as a manual tester I asked for some development work, the completion of which went some way to convincing them to hire me as a developer.

I worked on public facing websites for big multinationals such as Triumph motorcycles, Kia cars, and Orange, using the .NET stack. We didn't have much of a development process apart from hacking things out, but a colleague did lend me a book on XP sowing the seeds of my future

development.

Sharkbite Surf Shop, Bristol

Feb 2005 - Oct 2005 : Shop Assistant to Web Developer

I managed to negotiate a day a week out of the shop to design and build a small e-commerce site in Classic ASP. This gave me my first taste of production development and enough skills to land some work experience at E3Media.

In My Own Time

When I'm not staring at a screen I'm fairly active. I do a bit of skateboarding even though I'm old enough to know better, some very amateur surfing, and I'm currently the captain of Coolhurst's 7th men's tennis team, looking forward to playing in Middlesex East Division 6 Summer League this summer, after four straight promotions.

Security Clearance

SC Security Clearance - Lapsed

Education

University of Bristol (2003 - 2004) MSc Computer Science

Liverpool John Moores (1997 - 2000) BA (hons.) Business Administration

The Woodroffe School, Lyme Regis (1992 - 1997) A-Levels and GCSEs